Guide to the Harold Holzer Collection of Lincolniana 1860-1939 PR 402
New-York Historical Society
Harold Holzer collection of Lincolniana
1860-1939
New-York Historical Society
Holzer, Harold
PR 402
2.5 Linear feet in 2 boxes and 2 oversize folders.
Approximately 36 prints of Abraham Lincoln, Jefferson Davis, Robert E. Lee, and Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee assembled by Lincoln scholar Harold Holzer.
Arrangement
The Harold Holzer Collection of Lincolniana is organized in five series:
Series I.
Ephemera relating to Jefferson Davis and Robert E. Lee, circa 1862-1889, undated
Series II.
Engravings of Lincoln from the campaign period, 1860
Series III.
Memorial prints of Lincoln, 1870s-1900
Series IV.
Prints issued after Lincoln's death, 1866-1898, undated
Series V.
Prints of Lincoln from the late 19th and early 20th centuries, 1899-1939, undated
This material was offered, but went unsold, in Swann Auction Galleries sale 2486, "Printed & Manuscript Americana Featuring the Holzer Collection of Lincolniana," on September 27, 2018. Series I corresponds to Swann lot 40; Series II to lot 95; Series III to lots 133 and 144; Series IV to lot 145; and Series V to lot 148. For details, see the auction catalog.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Holzer (born 1949), longtime administrator at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and later director of Hunter College's Roosevelt House Public Policy Institute, purchased his first piece of Lincolniana when barely out of his teens. At twenty-two he began focusing on collecting engravings and lithographs of Lincoln. Originally he sought evocative imagery with which to decorate his home, but the materials inspired a lifelong scholarly inquiry that has resulted in over forty books on Lincoln and the Civil War. (See www.haroldholzer.com.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harold Holzer, 2018 (accession no. PPAC.2018.067).
Scope and Contents
Aside from a few portraits of Jefferson Davis, Robert E. Lee, and Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee, this collection is focused on imagery of Abraham Lincoln (including two of his Springfield, Illinois home) created during his lifetime (e.g., the campaign period, 1860), in response to his death, and later in the 19th- and through the mid-20th century.
Broadsides (notices); Chromolithographs; Engravings (prints); Lithographs.; Paper money.; Portraits.; Bilane, Ruth Witzel, 1915-2007; Buttre, John Chester, 1821-1893; Cole, Timothy, 1852-1931; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889 -- Pictorial works; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870 -- Pictorial works; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Pictorial works; Marshall, William Edgar, 1837-1906; Wall, Bernhardt, 1872-1956
- Series I. Ephemera relating to Jefferson Davis and Robert E. Lee, circa 1862-1889, undated
  - "Southern Rights", undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Uncredited engraving in blue and red depicting Jefferson Davis.
  - Confederate currency (3 pieces), 1862, 1864 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Confederate currency in one, ten, and fifty dollar denominations, the latter bill with a portrait of Jefferson Davis.
  - Portrait of Jefferson Davis, [1889] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Engraving by "Illman Brothers from a photograph taken a few months before his death" above facsimile signature.
  - Portraits of Robert E. Lee (2), 1863 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Hand-colored engraving clipped from an unidentified (probably British) periodical captioned "The Civil War in America: General Lee, Commander of the Confederate Army in Northern Virginia.--From a sketch by our special artist," February 14, 1863, with a black-and-white version of the same image as published in Harper's Weekly, March 14, 1863, with the caption "The Rebel General R. E. Lee.--From a late drawing by Mr. Vizetelly."
  - Portraits of Robert E. Lee (2), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Two engraved portraits of Robert E. Lee clipped from publications, possibly Harper's Weekly or Frank Leslie's.
  - Prospectus for Genealogical History of the Lee Family, of Virginia and Maryland, from A.D. 1200 to 1866, [circa 1871] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Edward C. Mead's Genealogical History of the Lee Family, of Virginia and Maryland, from A.D. 1200 to 1866 was issued by the University Publishing Company, New York, in 1871.
  - Portrait of Robert E. Lee (2 versions), [1871] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Plate from Edward C. Mead's Genealogical History of the Lee Family, of Virginia and Maryland, from A.D. 1200 to 1866 (New York: University Publishing Company, 1871). This and the corresponding portrait of Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee (Box 1, Folder 8) were displayed in the 1987-88 traveling exhibition "The Confederate Image."
  - Portrait of Mary Anna Randolph Custis Lee, [1871] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Plate from Edward C. Mead's Genealogical History of the Lee Family, of Virginia and Maryland, from A.D. 1200 to 1866 (New York: University Publishing Company, 1871). This and the corresponding portrait of Robert E. Lee (Box 1, Folder 7) were displayed in the 1987-88 traveling exhibition "The Confederate Image."
- Series II. Engravings of Lincoln from the campaign period, 1860
  - After Charles Barry. [Abraham Lincoln] (2), 1860 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Two examples, one on tinted chine-collé.
  - After Charles Barry (pirated). [Abraham Lincoln], 1860 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    Uncredited, but apparently pirated lithograph of the Charles Barry campaign print.
  - J. C. Buttre. "A. Lincoln" (narrow margins), 1860 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Engraved by J. C. Buttre after a photograph by Matthew Brady.
  - J. C. Buttre. "A. Lincoln" (wide margins), 1860 (Oversize FF-1, Item 1)
  - H. Wright Smith. "A. Lincoln", 1860 (Oversize FF-1, Item 2)
    Published by Benj. B. Russell, Boston.
  - "Abraham Lincoln's Residence", 1860 (Oversize FF-1, Item 3)
    Unattributed hand-colored engraving.
- Series III. Memorial prints of Lincoln, 1870s-1900
  - Carquillat, after Allardet. [Abraham Lincoln], 1870s? (Box 2)
    Framed, woven silk portrait of Lincoln.
  - Fishel, Adler & Schwartz. "Abraham Lincoln", circa 1875-1900 (Oversize FF-1, Item 4)
    Engraving featuring Lincoln's head on Andrew Jackson's body. Published in New York, late 19th century.
- Series IV. Prints issued after Lincoln's death, 1866-1898, undated
  - Kurz & Allison. [Abraham Lincoln], circa 1875-1900 (Oversize FF-1, Item 5)
    Untitled chromolithograph portrait of Lincoln. Published in Chicago, late 19th century.
  - [Lincoln consoling a standing child], undated (Oversize FF-1, Item 6)
  - Wm. E. Marshall. "Abraham Lincoln", 1866 (Oversize FF-2, Item 7)
    Published by Ticknor & Fields, Boston, 1866.
  - After Wm. E. Marshall. [Abraham Lincoln], undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Small untitled imitation of the Marshall engraving, in an oval frame.
  - Rees. "Abraham Lincoln's Return Home After His Successful Campaign for the Presidency of the United States, in October, 1860", [1898] (Oversize FF-2, Item 8)
    Colored lithograph published by Rees Print & Litho Co., Omaha, Nebraska.
- Series V. Prints of Lincoln from the late 19th and early 20th centuries, 1899-1939, undated
  - Ruth Witzel Bilane (1915-2007) after the Marshall print. [Abraham Lincoln], undated (Oversize FF-2, Item 9)
    Signed by the artist in pencil, Union, New Jersey.
  - Timothy Cole. [Abraham Lincoln], 1928 (Oversize FF-2, Item 10)
    Untitled engraving printed by Helen Fagg.
  - After Hesler. "Abraham Lincoln as he Appeared Directly after his Nomination in 1860", undated (Oversize FF-2, Item 11)
    Gravure of Hesler photograph, published by H. C. Brown & Co., New York.
  - Rea, after Deigendesch. "Lincoln: He was a Type of the True Elder Race", 1899 (Oversize FF-2, Item 12)
    Engraving published by McCaskey, Lancaster, Pennsylvania.
  - Bernhardt Wall. "Alexander Gardner's Photograph Gallery", 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    "Alexander Gardner's Photograph Gallery, Washington, D. C. Here President Lincoln sat for some portraits. Collection of the Public Library of the District of Columbia."
  - Bernhardt Wall. "Brady's Studio, Washington D.C.", 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    "Brady's Studio, Washington, D.C., where President Lincoln sat for some photographic portraits. Collection of L. C. Handy Studios, Washington, D.C."
  - Bernhardt Wall. "Cooper Union, New York City", 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    "Cooper Union, New York City, where Lincoln made his great speech, Monday evening, Feb. 27, 1860. He was escorted by William Cullen Bryant and David Dudley Field. Collection of New-York Historical Society."
  - Bernhardt Wall. "Lincoln and James A. Briggs attended Plymouth Church", 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
    "Lincoln and James A. Briggs attended Plymouth Church, Brooklyn, to hear Henry W. Beecher preach, March 11, 1860. Collection of New-York Historical Society."
  - Bernhardt Wall. "Lincoln, for the first time saw a printing press", 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    "Lincoln, for the first time saw a printing press at the Western Sun, or The Indiana Gazette, now The Vincennes Sun, as he was passing thru in March 1830."